so the question is why should I meditate
it's clearly something that a person can
be asking oneself regardless of how long
you have been meditating before whether
you're just starting you've been doing
it for years it's a it's good to remind
yourself of the context of the
fundamental reason that they turned you
towards meditation in the first place
towards Buddhist meditation it is so I
mean you could you know you can provide
an answer for it or you could you could
use it as a reflective tool that
question of why should I meditate even
if you know why you should meditate he
doesn't you can only benefit from
reviewing your mind and re-establishing
the right context for right context and
the clarity of the purpose of meditation
hmm so that's the that's the thing here
you can you can learn when you go to
meditate you can ask yourself for
example why am i meditating why am i
doing this don't just sit and do and go
through motions of of various techniques
but actually ask yourself what is my
motivation for doing this in the first
place what am I trying to achieve now
obviously depending on the answer there
your reflection can can go in various
directions but for example one of the
obvious answers would be freedom from
suffering or for example mmm less
specific but equally valid it would be
peace hmm so many everybody everybody
values peace mental peace so probably
one of the the most common reasons for
people turning to meditation is because
they want to they want to be able to
develop a peaceful mind
so you know you can you can go into some
sort of half-awake absorptions
mmm that can then approximate a peaceful
feeling but even that it's not a
guarantee that you always gonna get it
if you sit through like and then watch
tip of your nose and the mechanical
technique of concentration and so on
sometimes you might result in a peaceful
feeling but sometimes you want so
instead of just taking that for granted
you should investigate it why is it that
sometimes I'm peaceful sometimes or not
can I be peaceful at at will
at my own will why do I have to rely on
on going through certain motions of my
meditation techniques so that it will
then it will result in a peaceful
feeling maybe is it possible to directly
think peace and be peaceful by thinking
peace and the good news is it is
possible but the bad news is it's in a
completely opposite direction from where
meditation techniques are usually taking
you so instead of just mechanically
observing bodily sensations and similar
things you should really investigate the
clarity of purpose behind behind your
present sort of technique and so on so
develop like a peripheral context they
then all you need to do is think about
it and that context is their established
and if you think about it rightly means
you partake in that context if it if the
context is context of peace all you need
to do is fully understand what that
context is and you will be peaceful
regardless of the of the technique
regardless of the circumstances and so
on so you can use it as a reflection you
can ask yourself okay so I'm meditating
because I want to be peaceful do I know
what peace is
or maybe don't even necessarily imply
whether you know not just ask yourself
what is peace for me what do I think
peace is how would I describe these if
somebody comes here and asks me what is
peace why would I tell them it's not
necessarily right or wrong answer just
how would you designate it in your own
words to someone else how would you
convey it
so that's something again you can dwell
on that not I keep repeating this
because it's obviously tendency never
mind to jump on to looking for a right
answer but this is this is more like a
descriptive method describing what's
already there and through doing so
developing clarity in regard to it so
there isn't really a right or wrong
answer it's right if you're aiming in
the right direction it isn't right based
on the content of your answer so as long
as you're questioning it rightly it's
right even if you don't necessarily say
the right words because whatever you use
to designate the peaceful feeling at the
time it is standing for it in that
designation so it is something that
corresponds to what you're experiencing
so you're learning how to think
concretely think what is present without
overdoing without undoing we get down
negating there the presence of of that
peaceful feeling and that's how you get
to understand it you see the nature of
it nature of it that he has a reason
that it's that it is enduring on its own
and by seeing that you get to see then
the attitudes that you have been
exercising in regard to that independent
feeling be pleasant unpleasant or
neutral peaceful feeling and and only by
seeing that you can realize that that's
where the problem was it wasn't that you
were not experiencing peace on the level
of feeling it was like even when you
were experiencing peace and another
feeling you were not peaceful because of
your attitude towards your own feelings
attitudes of craving so for as long as
you don't understand what the feeling is
you don't see the extent of the feeling
you're not gonna see the extent of your
own craving in regard to it it's just
impossible so think about how would you
designate a peaceful feeling even if
it's even if you're not necessarily
peaceful how would you designate a peaceful
how would you designate a peaceful
feeling as a goal of your meditation
what what would it be will it be a like
a non disturbance yeah okay
what constitutes disturbance then
clarify that don't jump into the answer
let let your thoughts endure a bit once
you ask a question let it sort of resist
don't let your mind forget about it but
don't over focus on it either so what
constitutes disturbance what is
disturbance what is in common to every
disturbance that you have ever
experienced in your life what's in
common is that it is unpleasant always
something would have not been designated
as disturbance if it were Pleasant is no
such thing as Pleasant disturbance if
it's Pleasant it's not then disturbing
isn't it so then the disturbance is
always unpleasant but then you can ask
yourself a next question if would it be
possible for example to experience
disturbance but not suffer on account of
it and then again you can you can
reflect on that and see that they were
instances in the past I'm sure whereby
disturbing things things they used to
make you suffer
they will disturb you you would go
through them but you would not
necessarily suffer or not necessarily
suffer to the same extent but if the
suffering is truly rooted in that
unpleasantness of this of a disturbance
means you would always suffer to the
same extent it's just you wouldn't be
you wouldn't be even self aware of
suffering so suffering would have been
part of the disturbance but the fact
that disturbance is there but then
suffering sometimes it's like sometimes
is to some extent sometimes there isn't
any means there is something else there
that causes that suffering because if it
were truly solely rooted in
circumstantial disturbances - you would
be unaware of it
in other words disturbance will to the
same extent equal suffering
always there wouldn't be there would be
no discrepancy and in some occasions
like men for example with you in a good
mood even even some heavy serious
disturbances still don't make you suffer
your mood doesn't change but if you move
this fully dependent fully determined by
their by the circumstances disturbing or
non disturbing circumstances then then
we will not possess'd good mood would
not possess the midst disturbances yet
it persists even for an ignorant mind so
that means that you can't say that
you're suffering your bad moods are
rooted in the circumstantial
disturbances because it doesn't always
correspond to them so it's it's that
realization of that discrepancy that's
what gives you that's basically the room
where the practice is initially it feels
very narrow obviously but the more you
dwell on it the why that it becomes
remove the most space you get because
through reflection you're clarifying it
and you're clarifying what I said before
your attitude in regard to the
disturbing unpleasant feeling or or a
neutral peaceful feeling or the
agreeable Pleasant feeling and so on so
you are liable to these things they come
and go they endure the feelings one at a
time but it's your own attitude in
regard to the determines then whether
whether your mood will be affected or
not whether you will suffer or not so
then that takes us to the next question
which is if if you're not suffering in
your mood amidst disturbances
disagreeable disturbances unpleasant
sight sound smell taste touches thoughts
words of others but your mood doesn't
change in some occasion so easy then
right to say that absence of that
basically peace is found in on this
servants of the environment wouldn't be
more accurate saying pieces than found
in non disturbance of your mood so you
could see how first we started from
disturbing environment non disturbing
environment but now you realize that
it's actually you moved in regard to the
environment that's what your suffering
is so if there is no suffering on the
level of your mood doesn't matter the
environment your imperturbable in regard
to the environment but now you can take
that another step further from the world
on to the mind mood of your mind but now
you can apply the same principle and
then reflect upon question are you in
charge of your own moods today do your
moods originate at your will or do they
arise on their own cease on their own
and endure on their own for as long as
they want in you the answer is quite
obvious but that's the thing don't
necessarily rush in giving that answer
allow this question to India because
question forces you to look at the
answer answering it makes you look at
something else
letting question endure it's sort of
pushing in the direction of the answer
so am I in control of my moods as a
question let it into your den don't jump
in answering the don't ignore it either
so whichever my mood is currently
present mi-2 create Rowlett am I in
charge like if it were to cease can I
prevent it from doing so if it were to
increase can I prevent it from doing so
you realize it's inconceivable and it's
really just not dwelling long enough on
the nature of of this being
inconceivable that's why you use sort of
ignore it and then start acting out of
belief as if the mood is yours but the
mood is ease it's a container of your
experience a particular coloring to it
particular weather to it what you do
within that as in choices you make and
intentions upon which you act that's on
you but the container of the of the of
the weather it's pretty much on the
level of those circumstantial
disturbances or non disturbances so
through reflecting like this you started
with a disturbance comes from the world
then oh well disturbance actually comes
from the mood and I realized oh
disturbance doesn't even come from the
move because mood is not in my control
disturbing calm disturbance comes from
my choices in my intentions in regard to
the mood I'm experiencing in regard to
the feeling I'm experiencing and that's
why the bully would often sum up his
entire teaching if I don't do anything
that's rooted in unwholesome as in don't
act out of intentions that are based on
greed aversion delusion and act upon
intention that are based on non-green on
a version on delusion that will purify
your mind whether you want it or not but
see you can be acting good and no or
proper but if you still hold the view
that the root of your suffering is in
the world or in the mood or in all sorts
of things but in your choices means
you're still everything you do whether
good or bad is undermined underlined by
the wrong
and that's a problem so that's really
why you should be meditating to abandon
the wrong view and develop peace on
account of it then your meditation will
be about maintaining that wholesome
peace because as we just clarified
disturbance the peace or absence of
peace does not come from the external
disturbances doesn't even come from your
moods comes from your own craving
perpetuated by your desire and lust and
intentions in regard to the moods that
are persisting so in a bad mood your
actions will be revolving around denying
it trying to get rid of it you'll be oh
your mind will be occupied by that it
will be rooted in that good mood again
your mind will be overly welcoming it
will indulging it overly binding itself
to it as you know this is mine this is
great it will last forever and in the
neutral mood which in itself it's
actually what the piece is neutral
feeling neutral mood the mind well the
mind turns towards anything anything
they will cause it to feel anything
other than then that neutral feeling
because in itself the neutral feeling is
it's unpleasant with the mind that it
still has the habits of ignoring it's
unpleasant in in as much as boredom is
unpleasant that results in anxiety that
is very unpleasant so the the the
neutral the neutral mood is something
that can be what your actions in regard
to the neutral mood is something that
can be gradually cultivated to the point
of where you stop resisting the neutral
mood stop trying to distract yourself
from it and only then you can get to
recognize the peace within that that's
what he would have said the neutral
feeling is unpleasant when it's unknown
and pleasant when known and he said it's
the feeling that the wise people would
praise as a neutral feeling the loftiest
of all feelings but in itself because
everybody starts with ignorance so experiencing
starts with ignorance so experiencing
neutral feeling with ignorance gonna be
unpleasant so in other words if you
recognize that you yourself is not free
you're not free from ignorance you have
to be careful in taking what you think
peace is for granted because on the only
true way of knowing what peaceful is is
to abandon ignorance its pleasant peace
is pleasant when it's known when it's
understood so if you know that you
haven't necessarily made any significant
understanding that you can explain to
yourself or even others yet here you are
chasing a certain standard of peace that
you assumed means you're most likely
going to be acting out of sensuality and
craving towards Pleasant feeling which
for you it's peaceful so nobody's like
I'm not saying that there is no peaceful
feeling even for Petrosian there is but
he should not take it for granted as
that which truly peaceful is because it
isn't the true peace is when ignorance
is abandoned not when circumstances are
suppressed and controlled and managed
and measured it's when the mind cannot
be disturbed
amidst the disturbances that's what
peace is and the only way for mind to
not be disturbed amidst disturbances
Eastern understanding what truly
disturbance is or where the disturbance
truly comes from and when you recognize
it comes from your gratuitous attitude
of assuming ownership of your moods of
your environment of your circumstances
of your senses then you will stop doing
it because it becomes like understanding
that this is not in your control becomes
incompatible with the behavior that
assumes control of those things so you
don't have to then make an extra effort
to stop assume automatically your
behavior will change because you have
uprooted the assumption upon which it
was based
so the peaceful feeling is then when
there is absence of craving sorry the
peace the peace is when there is absence
of craving in regard to what's being
felt at a time so when you sit down and
meditate as we just done with this whole
reflection self reflection self
interrogation as the Buddha would often
be encouraged amongst to do you realize
that you are at peace not when there are
no disturbances externally or bad moods
internally you're at peace when there is
no craving in regard to the disagreeable
feeling where the disagreeable of the
bad mood or disagreeable of the
environment and there will be no craving
in regard to disagreeable when you fully
understand the disagreeable agreeable
and neutral as a reason on its own which
is another word saying impermanent not
created by me not for me on its own
circumstantially reason induce I don't
need to rush and get rid of its presence
no I can allow it in your because it
does not concern me and it will stop
concerning you when you fully understand
that it cannot concern you and it cannot
concern you when you fully understand it
it has a reason on its own it's
impermanent and so on so it all revolves
around the same principles same
understanding of the same universal
natures of phenomena in this case
feelings in states of mind so then if
you want to cultivate peace you just
have to cultivate indifference towards
present enduring moods present enduring
feelings if you cultivate indifference
sufficiently to the sufficient extent
you will basically stop perpetuating
your craving
through negligent acts they were rooted
in it and that is truly peaceful
then you wouldn't be afraid even of
things that used to cause you anxiety is
a fear is a bad mood and so on because
you're above your moods now as well the
weather still comes and goes and changes
but none of that affects your intentions
and the clarity of your of your of your
vision of your mindfulness of you
understanding and if the mind can
establish itself upon the context of
peace that we just described you can do
so it will the clearer the context
becomes the easier your meditation and
mental establishment is that's where
monks have been properly developed they
would say oh I can obtain jhanas it will
literally you will them they're there
because they're the context the
peripheral context they transcend the
domain of sensuality you will even
thinking and pondering in the second
jhana the movement of the thoughts even
that you go beyond and it's all through
clarifying the peripheral context of
your currently currently a present
situation and currently enduring
feelings or feeling they're not many
enduring at the same time it's always
wanted to hit at a time on that general
level so we're back where we started
non disturbance then is what pieces is
what absence of craving in regard to
your current situation yes and that's
something you can see that that context
can you can develop even when you're not
necessarily sitting cross-legged and
meditating it can stay at the back of
your mind even when you're going around
walking extending your arms eating going
to toilet as the with the man is time
descry said the monk and to jhana oh no
actually I think he was doing by himself
he said he would enter Jannah and that
stay will be so divine his mind will be
established upon the divine and then he
said whether he he walks sits down it's
goes to the toilet whatever he does in
that state it's also divine because the
mind is established upon the divine
state of jhana divine meaning lofty
meaning transcended the the sensual base
the transcending the concern with the
senses transcendent intentions rooted in
the senses and the only way to do that
is to fully understand what those
intentions are to fully recognize the
domain of it and that's how you go
beyond and this is how you do it as we
just done through self questioning
because each time you ask the question
even if your question is not necessarily
very accurate it at least it's turning
you in the direction you should be going
like what is underneath this that I'm
doing right now basically questioning is
forcing you to become self-aware without
making that self-awareness into another
thing you're doing mechanically because
that's the point you want to avoid the
mechanical repetition of a meditation
technique mindlessness so why am i
meditating because i want peace do i
have to wait for that peace then if the
sole basis for peace is absence of
craving right here right now no you
don't all you need to do is stop craving
right here right now you stop craving by
realizing the things you crave in regard
to are indifferent to your own craving
makes no difference then you're craving
becomes redundant so you can't
intentionally stop craving but you can
certainly through discernment of what
you are craving in regard to you can
evaporate it you can stop feeding your
craving and it will be the way through
that repetitive effort every clarifying
that which you already know
so then you just remind yourself or
something else can remind you things
that you used to crave once you abandon
craving those things arise and there is
no claiming and reminds you that you are
free from craving and if you're another
hand remind you that you're completely
free from craving and again I think
there was summer in the suitors where
and I think somebody has the Buddha
where they aren't constantly experience
pleasure of enlightenment I said no
initially then they become you know he
gets used to it becomes normal and then
he would experience it whenever things
they used to cause the defilements to
arise he would encounter them in the
world and then he would remind him that
there are no defilements they used to
arise so it's just like memory of all
you remember how used to be and I
realize you're incapable you're
incapable of suffering you're incapable
of craving you're capable of lasting
incapable of having a version in your
will and that reminder reminds you comes
with a pleasure as well so whether you
doing walking meditation sitting
meditation especially if you still don't
have the right view you really want to
be aiming in that clarifying the context
of your actions and then discerning the
basis upon which you gratuitously
maintain the attitude of craving I want
more of this I want less of that and so
on and that will result in in a peace in
mental equanimity